1. Title

Chronological, geochemical and sedimentological data from a lake sediment record extracted from Lake L5 (Matias Lake) on Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands in 2011.

2. Abstract

The dataset comprises of lake site photos, data and multiproxy data from Lake L5 (aka Matias Lake), a small lake basin at 62.2450°S, 58.6655°W on Potter Peninsula, King George Island, South Shetland Islands. The data have been used to constrain deglaciation and glacier dynamics on Potter Peninsula. 

Data for the Lake L5 (Matias Lake) sediment record consist of downcore measurements of chronology, geochemistry, and sedimentology proxy data collected from the depocentre in November 2011.

3. Funding source

Data collected in this study were funded by: Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias de la Tierra (CICTERRA), the Dirección Nacional del Antártico/Instituto Antártico Argentino (DNA/IAA) in the framework of the Project PICTA, 2011 – 0102, IAA “Geomorfología y Geología Glaciar del Archipiélago James Ross e Islas Shetland del Sur, Sector Norte de la Península Antártica”; the Alfred Wegener Institute (AWI) research program Polar regions and Coasts in a changing Earth System (PACES II); IMCONet (FP7 IRSES, action no. 318718); the Natural Environment Research Council (NERC/BAS-CGS Grant no.81); the NERC/BAS science programmes CACHE-PEP: Natural climate variability – extending the Americas palaeoclimate transect through the Antarctic Peninsula to the pole and GRADES-QWAD: Quaternary West Antarctic Deglaciations. We thank the crews of the Argentine research station “Carlini'' and the adjoined German Dallmann-Labor (AWI) Laboratory, the Uruguayan research station “Artigas”, the Russian Bellingshausen Station, the Chinese Great Wall Station, Base Presidente Eduardo Frei Montalva, the Brazilian Navy Almirante Maximiano, the UK Navy HMS Endurance and NERC/BAS James Clark Ross for logistical support during the 2006, 2011, 2014 and 2015 field seasons. 

4. Keywords

Deglaciation; geomorphological mapping; radiocarbon dating; South Shetland Islands; stratigraphy; glacial readvance

5. Personnel

Data collectors & analysts (ORCID code)

Stephen J. Roberts1 (0000-0001-5542-3703) – sediment core extraction, chronology, geochemistry, sedimentology
Emma J. Pearson2 – sediment core extraction, geochemistry
Tamara Manograsso Czalbowski3 – sediment core extraction, chronology, geochemistry, sedimentology
Sarah J. Davies4 – geochemistry
Martin Grosjean5  – geochemistry
Stephanie Arcusa5 – geochemistry
Bianca Perren1 – geochemistry

Affiliations

1British Antarctic Survey, Natural Environment Research Council, High Cross, Madingley Road, Cambridge, CB3 0ET, UK.
2School of Geography, Politics and Sociology, Newcastle University, Newcastle-upon-Tyne, NE1 7RU, UK.
 3Instituto Antártico Argentino (I.A.A.), Av. 25 de Mayo. San Martín. Provincia de Buenos Aires (CP1650), Argentina.
4Department of Geography and Earth Sciences, Aberystwyth University, Aberystwyth, SY23 3DB, UK.
5 Institute of Geography and Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern, Switzerland 

6. Lineage/methodology

Core collection
Sediment cores were collected using a Livingston piston corer from the deepest point (~5 m of water depth) in Matias Lake (L5: 62.2450°S, 58.6655°W, ~70-75 m a.s.l., 20-30 cm total recovered sediment depth). We extracted 13 short cores from the depocentre in Matias Lake and along a surface transect towards Rudy Lake. Sediment recovery depth ranged from 20 and 60 cm before encountering an impenetrable diamicton layer. Data from cores MAT1 (L5-H1) (27 cm) and MAT2 (L5-H2) (29 cm) extracted from the deepest part of Matias Lake (5.8 m; 62° 14' 42.054"S, 58° 39' 53.82"W) are included in this dataset.

Chronology
Obtaining basal radiocarbon ages from basal and bulk minerogenic sediments in the Matias Lake cores proved challenging due to a general lack of organic carbon.Pb-210 Cs-137 and Am-241 dating of the uppermost 10 cm of the lake sediment records was undertaken and dating model calculations followed standard procedures defined in Appleby and Oldfield (1978). Pb-210 age estimates were derived using the constant rate of supply (CRS) method (Appleby and Oldfield, 1978) and incorporated into Bayesian age-depth models. The Pb-210 Constant Rate of Supply (CRS) age model shows that the uppermost 10 cm have been deposited since c. 1850 CE, and the well-defined 137Cs peak at 5 cm depth is coherent with the Pb-210 age model. 

Geochemistry & Sedimentology
GEOTEK-MSCL: Physical properties (gamma-ray density (GRD), magnetic susceptibility, fractional porosity, resistivity and impedance) were measured using Geotek® multi-sensor core logger (MSCL).

ITRAX-XRF: Non-destructive ITRAX (Cox Analytical) micro-X-ray fluorescence (μ-XRF) and Bartington Magnetic Susceptibility High Resolution Surface Scanning Sensor (MS2E) measurements were undertaken at Aberystwyth University. Contiguous bulk, wet sediment geochemical Energy Dispersive XRF-CS (Energy Dispersive Spectroscopy) analysis was obtained using a chromium (Cr) X-ray tube (X-radiography image settings: 40 kV, 40 mA, 200 ms; XRF-CSCr settings: 30 kV, 40 mA, dwell time of 10 seconds, at 100 μm or 2 mm. 

SPECIM: Hyperspectral image (HSI) scanning was performed using the Specim Ltd. single core scanner (PFD-CL-65-V10E line scan camera, 400–1000 nm) according to the protocol of Butz et al. (2015). The spatial resolution (pixel size) was set at 69 μm x 69 μm and the spectral resolution is 2.8 nm sampled at an interval of 0.78 nm. Raw data were normalised with a BaSO4 reference and spectral endmembers were calculated using the software ENVI 5.03. Quantitative estimates of pigments were obtained using the Relative Absorption Band Depth (RABD) method, which uses ratios and normalised reflectance data from distinct wavelengths. The spectral index RABD660;670 (RABD at 660-670 nm) was calculated from the continuum between 590 and 730 nm (Butz et al., 2015) with I-band wavelengths between 660 and 670 nm using equations RABD660;670 = (6*R590+7*R730)/13/Rmin(660;670) and RABD660;670 [I-Band] = (6*R590+7*R730)/13/ Rmin(660;670)/Rmean (Rein and Sirocko, 2002).

Additional statistical analysis was undertaken, and figures constructed, using R v. 4.1.0/RStudio v. 1.4.1717 (primarily packages Tidyverse, ggplot2, Vegan, Rioja, Ggally v. 2.1.2, RBacon, Rcarbon, Bchron), Sigmaplot v. 14.0, C2 (Juggins, 2007), MATLAB v. R2021a, with final layouts achieved in Adobe Illustrator v. 26.2.1 or CorelDRAW v. 2020. Code, data, all packages used, and package references can be found at: https://github.com/stever60/Potter_Peninsula 

7. Instrumentation

Chronology
Pb-210 Cs-137 and Am-241 dating of the uppermost 10 cm of the lake sediment records was undertaken on a well-type gamma spectrometry (Ge-detector, GWC 2522-7500 SL, Canberra Industries Inc., USA) and processed with GENIE 2000 3.0 (Canberra Industries Inc., USA).

Geochemistry & Sedimentology
ITRAX XRF core scanner fitted with a Molybdenum (Mo) anode X-ray tube and a Bartington Magnetic Susceptibility High Resolution Surface Scanning Sensor (MS2E)

Geotek® multi-sensor core logger (MSCL)

Hyperspectral image (HSI) scanning was performed using the Specim Ltd. single core scanner (PFD-CL-65-V10E line scan camera, 400–1000 nm) according to the protocol of Butz et al. (2015).

8. Quality

Chronology
Pb-210 age estimates were derived using the constant rate of supply (CRS) method (Appleby and Oldfield, 1978) and incorporated into Bayesian age-depth models.

Geochemistry & Sedimentology
ITRAX-XRF Raw count per second (cps) data were analysed using the Q-spec software v8.6.0 (Cox Analytical), with MSE values minimised to optimise the fit of ‘as measured’ spectra to a modelled spectrum. Data are presented as percentages of the Total Scatter Normalised ratio sum (%∑TSN or, more simply, %TSN, which are equivalent to percentages of the cps sum, or %cps) to account for downcore variations in count rate, density, water and organic content. Data less than mean minus two-sigma kcps (mainly due to gaps in the core) and greater than MSE plus two-sigma (representing a poor fit between measured to modelled spectra) were filtered before analysis. ‘Noisy’ elements were eliminated by comparing cps and using %TSN thresholds of >0.1% mean and >0.5% maximum, and by examining autocorrelation profiles for each element. Elements are presented as natural log (log n or Ln) ratios.

9. Related datasets

Chronological and sedimentological data from Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands.

Chronological, geochemical and sedimentological data from a lake sediment record extracted from Lake L15 (GPS Lake) on Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands in 2011.

10. Related URLs

Code is available on: www.github.com/stever60/Potter_Peninsula 

11. Temporal coverage

Cores were extracted and data collected in November 2011 and cover the last 500 years

12. Spatial coverage

The L5-MAT1 record is from 62.2450°S, 58.6655°W, ~30 m a.s.l. and is 24 cm long

13. Resolution

GEOTEK MSCL data were measured at 2 mm intervals 
Geochemical XRF-Core scanning data were measured at 100 μm and 2 mm contiguous intervals. 
SPECIM hyperspectral data were measured at 69 μm intervals

14. Location

Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands

15. References

Appleby PG and Oldfield F. (1978) The calculation of lead-210 dates assuming a constant rate of supply of unsupported 210Pb to the sediment. CATENA 5: 1-8.

Butz C, Grosjean M, Fischer D, et al. (2015) Hyperspectral imaging spectroscopy: a promising method for the biogeochemical analysis of lake sediments. Journal of Applied Remote Sensing 9: 096031.

Heredia Barión P, Roberts SJ, Spiegel C, Binnie SA, Wacker L, Davies J, et al. (in review) Holocene deglaciation and glacier readvances on the Fildes Peninsula, King George Island, NW Antarctic Peninsula. The Holocene. https://doi.org/10.31223/X59S7S

Heredia Barión P, Strelin JA, Roberts SJ, Spiegel C, Wacker L, Niedermann S, et al. (in press). Holocene deglaciation, glacial dynamics and the geomorphology of Potter Peninsula, King George Island (Isla 25 de Mayo), NW Antarctic Peninsula. Frontiers in Earth Science. https://doi.org/10.31223/X5606J

Rein B and Sirocko F. (2002) In-situ reflectance spectroscopy – analysing techniques for high-resolution pigment logging in sediment cores. International Journal of Earth Sciences 91: 950-954.

16. Data structure and data format

This entry contains the following data folders and subfolders (in alphabetical order):
Chronology
      L5_MAT1A_Pb210.csv 
      CRS is constant rate of supply model; DMAR is dry mass accumulation rate

Geochemistry & sedimentology

GEOTEK data folder containing:
L5_GEOTEK_MSCL.csv – GEOTEK MSCL data for cores from Lake 5 (Matias Lake)

ITRAX data folder containing:
document_XRF.txt – run and set up data for the core section XRF scan
document_XRAD.txt – run and set up data for the core section radiography scan
optical.tif – raw optical image of the core section scan
optical1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed optical image of the core section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
radiograph.tif – raw X ray image of the core section scan
radiograph1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed X ray image of the core section scan section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
result.txt – summary set up and cps datafile for the core section
sumspectra.txt – average spectra output datafile the core section
XRF-spectra.zip folder – individual run data and spectra channel energy data for the core section in sequence from the top of the section, e.g., L000001.txt, L00001.txt etc. 
L5_MAT1A_Cr_100um_cps.csv – filtered cps X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data 
L5_MAT1A_Cr_2mm_%TSN.csv - %TSN (percentage of the total scatter normalised sum) X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data
L5_MAT1A_MS.csv – X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) MS data

SPECIM data folder containing:
L5_MAT1A_SPECIM.csv – summary of Specim data
L5_MAT1A_SPECIM_archive.zip – archive of Specim imagery and data 

Lake chemistry data folder containing:
L5_Water_chemistry.csv 

Notes: DO%: Run for 10-15 minutes to stabilise inside sealed beaker with damp sponge; Calibrated using atmospheric pressure of 1012.0 mbar (from Garmin barGPS); Air temp = -1oC; stable temp/press

Photos Folder containing:
L5_core_photos
L5_site_photos

17. Access constraints

None after publication but a log in for reviewers to access an embargoed dataset is needed.

18. Use constraints

NERC-funded data, so the Open Government Licence applies.




