1. Title
Chronological, geochemical and sedimentological data from a lake sediment record extracted from Lake L15 (GPS Lake) on Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands in 2011.

2. Abstract
The dataset comprises of lake site photos, data and multiproxy data from Lake L15 (aka GPS Lake), a small lake basin at 62° 14' 26.052"S, 58° 40' 39.36"W on Potter Peninsula, King George Island, South Shetland Islands. The data have been used to constrain deglaciation and glacier dynamics on Potter Peninsula. 

Data for the Lake L15 (GPS Lake) sediment record consist of downcore measurements of chronology, geochemistry, and sedimentology proxy data collected from the depocentre in November 2011.

3. Funding source
Data collected in this study were funded by: Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias de la Tierra (CICTERRA), the Dirección Nacional del Antártico/Instituto Antártico Argentino (DNA/IAA) in the framework of the Project PICTA, 2011 – 0102, IAA “Geomorfología y Geología Glaciar del Archipiélago James Ross e Islas Shetland del Sur, Sector Norte de la Península Antártica”; the Alfred Wegener Institute (AWI) research program Polar regions and Coasts in a changing Earth System (PACES II); IMCONet (FP7 IRSES, action no. 318718); the Natural Environment Research Council (NERC/BAS-CGS Grant no.81); the NERC/BAS science programmes CACHE-PEP: Natural climate variability – extending the Americas palaeoclimate transect through the Antarctic Peninsula to the pole and GRADES-QWAD: Quaternary West Antarctic Deglaciations. We thank the crews of the Argentine research station “Carlini'' and the adjoined German Dallmann-Labor (AWI) Laboratory, the Uruguayan research station “Artigas”, the Russian Bellingshausen Station, the Chinese Great Wall Station, Base Presidente Eduardo Frei Montalva, the Brazilian Navy Almirante Maximiano, the UK Navy HMS Endurance and NERC/BAS James Clark Ross for logistical support during the 2006, 2011, 2014 and 2015 field seasons. 

4. Keywords
Deglaciation; geomorphological mapping; radiocarbon dating; South Shetland Islands; stratigraphy; glacial readvance

5. Personnel
Data collectors & analysts (ORCID code)
Stephen J. Roberts1 (0000-0001-5542-3703) – sediment core extraction, chronology, geochemistry, sedimentology
Emma J. Pearson2 – sediment core extraction, geochemistry
Tamara Manograsso Czalbowski3 – sediment core extraction, chronology, geochemistry, sedimentology
Sarah J. Davies4 – geochemistry
Martin Grosjean5  – geochemistry
Stephanie Arcusa5 – geochemistry
Bianca Perren1 – geochemistry

Affiliations
1British Antarctic Survey, Natural Environment Research Council, High Cross, Madingley Road, Cambridge, CB3 0ET, UK.
2School of Geography, Politics and Sociology, Newcastle University, Newcastle-upon-Tyne, NE1 7RU, UK.
 3Instituto Antártico Argentino (I.A.A.), Av. 25 de Mayo. San Martín. Provincia de Buenos Aires (CP1650), Argentina.
4Department of Geography and Earth Sciences, Aberystwyth University, Aberystwyth, SY23 3DB, UK.
5 Institute of Geography and Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern, Switzerland 

6. Lineage/methodology
   Core collection
Sediment cores were collected using a Russian and Livingston corers from the deepest point (~2 m of water depth) in Lake L15 (GPS Lake) (L15: 62° 14' 26.052"S, 58° 40' 39.36"W, ~30 m a.s.l., 11-55 cm total recovered sediment depth). Eight cores were collected from a grid of 25 (~1 m spaced) holes drilled through the ~75-100 cm thick lake ice above the deepest accessible point (~2 m):  Data from L15-H2 (62° 14' 26.052"S, 58° 40' 39.36"W) with 30 cm of sediment and L15-H16  (62° 14' 26.016"S, 58° 40' 39.252"W) with 55 cm of sediment are  included in this dataset. Other cores taken at this site were:  L15-H4 = 11 cm, L15-H9 =  39 cm, L15-H17 = 45 cm, L15-H19 = 34 cm, L15-H20 = 61 cm and L15-H22 = 49 cm.

Chronology
Pb-210 Cs-137 and Am-241 dating of the uppermost 10 cm of the lake sediment records was undertaken and dating model calculations followed standard procedures defined in Appleby and Oldfield (1978). Pb-210 age estimates were derived using the constant rate of supply (CRS) method (Appleby and Oldfield, 1978) and incorporated into Bayesian age-depth models. The Pb-210 CRS age model produced a low sedimentation rate in the top 10 cm and the sample at ~4-5 cm is likely to be at least 150 years old. 

Radiocarbon ages of aquatic moss and macrophytic material from the uppermost lithological Unit 3 in Lake L15 were calibrated using the Southern Hemisphere SHCal20 calibration curve in Oxcal v. 4.4 (Hogg et al., 2020). Post-bomb (>1950 CE) ages were corrected according to 13C/12C isotopic ratios from measured pMC with the ‘present day’ pMC value defined as 107.5% (2010 CE) and calibrated using the SHCal13 SH Zone 1-2 Bomb curve in CALIBomb (Reimer and Reimer, 2004; Hua et al., 2013). Calibrated ages range from post 1950 CE to c. 0.6 ka cal BP.

Geochemistry & Sedimentology

Physical properties (gamma-ray density (GRD), magnetic susceptibility, fractional porosity, resistivity and impedance) were measured using Geotek® multi-sensor core logger (MSCL).

Non-destructive ITRAXTM (Cox Analytical) micro-X-ray fluorescence (μ-XRF) and Bartington Magnetic Susceptibility High Resolution Surface Scanning Sensor (MS2E) measurements were undertaken at Aberystwyth University. Contiguous bulk, wet sediment geochemical Energy Dispersive XRF-CS (Energy Dispersive Spectroscopy) analysis was obtained using a chromium (Cr) X-ray tube (X-radiography image settings: 40 kV, 40 mA, 200 ms; XRF-CSCr settings: 30 kV, 40 mA, dwell time of 10 seconds, at 100 μm or 2 mm. 

Hyperspectral image (HSI) scanning was performed using the Specim Ltd. single core scanner (PFD-CL-65-V10E line scan camera, 400–1000 nm) according to the protocol of Butz et al. (2015). The spatial resolution (pixel size) was set at 69 μm x 69 μm and the spectral resolution is 2.8 nm sampled at an interval of 0.78 nm. Raw data were normalised with a BaSO4 reference and spectral endmembers were calculated using the software ENVI 5.03. Quantitative estimates of pigments were obtained using the Relative Absorption Band Depth (RABD) method, which uses ratios and normalised reflectance data from distinct wavelengths. The spectral index RABD660;670 (RABD at 660-670 nm) was calculated from the continuum between 590 and 730 nm (Butz et al., 2015) with I-band wavelengths between 660 and 670 nm using equations RABD660;670 = (6*R590+7*R730)/13/Rmin(660;670) and RABD660;670 [I-Band] = (6*R590+7*R730)/13/ Rmin(660;670)/Rmean (Rein and Sirocko, 2002).

Additional statistical analysis was undertaken, and figures constructed, using R v. 4.1.0/RStudio v. 1.4.1717 (primarily packages Tidyverse, ggplot2, Vegan, Rioja, Ggally v. 2.1.2, RBacon, Rcarbon, Bchron), Sigmaplot v. 14.0, C2 (Juggins, 2007), MATLAB v. R2021a, with final layouts achieved in Adobe Illustrator v. 26.2.1 or CorelDRAW v. 2020. Code, data, all packages used, and package references can be found at: https://github.com/stever60/Potter_Peninsula 

7. Instrumentation
Chronology
Pb-210 Cs-137 and Am-241 dating of the uppermost 10 cm of the lake sediment records was undertaken on a well-type gamma spectrometry (Ge-detector, GWC 2522-7500 SL, Canberra Industries Inc., USA) and processed with GENIE 2000 3.0 (Canberra Industries Inc., USA).

Geochemistry & Sedimentology
Geotek® multi-sensor core logger (MSCL)

ITRAX XRF core scanner fitted with a Molybdenum (Mo) anode X-ray tube and a Bartington Magnetic Susceptibility High Resolution Surface Scanning Sensor (MS2E)

Hyperspectral image (HSI) scanning was performed using the Specim Ltd. single core scanner (PFD-CL-65-V10E line scan camera, 400–1000 nm) according to the protocol of Butz et al. (2015).

8. Quality

Chronology
Pb-210 age estimates were derived using the constant rate of supply (CRS) method (Appleby and Oldfield, 1978) and incorporated into Bayesian age-depth models. The prerequisite for the CRS model was not fulfilled because the flux of Pb-210 has changed through time and is not constant, but Pb-210 data are consistent with the radiocarbon ages that show sediment between 6 and 6.5 cm dates to 620±80 a cal BP, and 3–3.5 cm and 0–0.5 cm depth were deposited in the ‘post-bomb’ (post-1950 CE) era, most likely between -40 – -44 cal yr BP (1990–1994 CE) The Cs-137 data are inconsistent with the Pb-210 CRS age model and it is possible that the steep increase in Cs-137 in the upper 2 cm relates to a Cs-137 ‘soil reservoir’, which is leaching Cs-137 into the lake from snow or lake-ice melting.

Geochemistry & Sedimentology
ITRAX-XRF Raw count per second (cps) data were analysed using the Q-spec software v8.6.0 (Cox Analytical), with MSE values minimised to optimise the fit of ‘as measured’ spectra to a modelled spectrum. Data are presented as percentages of the Total Scatter Normalised ratio sum (%∑TSN or, more simply, %TSN, which are equivalent to percentages of the cps sum, or %cps) to account for downcore variations in count rate, density, water and organic content. Data less than mean minus two-sigma kcps (mainly due to gaps in the core) and greater than MSE plus two-sigma (representing a poor fit between measured to modelled spectra) were filtered before analysis. ‘Noisy’ elements were eliminated by comparing cps and using %TSN thresholds of >0.1% mean and >0.5% maximum, and by examining autocorrelation profiles for each element. Elements are presented as natural log (log n or Ln) ratios.

9. Related datasets
Chronological and sedimentological data from Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands.

Chronological, geochemical and sedimentological data from a lake sediment record extracted from Lake L5 (Matias Lake) on Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands in 2011.

10. Related URLs
Code is available on: www.github.com/stever60/Potter_Peninsula 

11. Temporal coverage
Cores were extracted and data collected in November 2011 and cover the last 500-1000 years

12. Spatial coverage
The L15-H2 record is from 62° 14' 26.052"S, 58° 40' 39.36"W, ~30 m a.s.l. and is 30 cm long
The L15-H6 record is from 62° 14' 26.016"S, 58° 40' 39.252"W, ~30 m a.s.l. and is 55 cm long

13. Resolution
GEOTEK MSCL data were measured at 2 mm intervals.
Geochemical XRF-Core scanning data were measured at 500 micron contiguous intervals. 
SPECIM hyperspectral data were measured at 69 μm intervals

14. Location
Potter Peninsula, South Shetland Islands

15. References
Appleby PG and Oldfield F. (1978) The calculation of lead-210 dates assuming a constant rate of supply of unsupported 210Pb to the sediment. CATENA 5: 1-8.

Butz C, Grosjean M, Fischer D, et al. (2015) Hyperspectral imaging spectroscopy: a promising method for the biogeochemical analysis of lake sediments. Journal of Applied Remote Sensing 9: 096031.

Heredia Barión P, Roberts SJ, Spiegel C, Binnie SA, Wacker L, Davies J, et al. (submitted - a) Mid–late Holocene deglaciation and glacier readvances on the Fildes Peninsula, King George Island, NW Antarctic Peninsula. The Holocene.

Heredia Barión P, Strelin JA, Roberts SJ, Spiegel C, Wacker L, Niedermann S, et al. (submitted - b). Holocene deglaciation, glacial dynamics and the geomorphology of Potter Peninsula, King George Island (Isla 25 de Mayo), NW Antarctic Peninsula. Frontiers in Earth Science.

Hogg AG, Heaton TJ, Hua Q, Palmer JG, Turney CSM, Southon J, et al. (2020) SHCal20 Southern Hemisphere Calibration, 0–55,000 Years cal BP. Radiocarbon 62: 759-778.

Hua Q, Barbetti M, and Rakowski AZ (2013). Atmospheric radiocarbon for the period 1950-2010. Radiocarbon 55, 1–14.

Reimer RW, and Reimer PJ. (2004). CALIBomb - calibration of post-bomb C-14 data (www.calib.org).

Rein B and Sirocko F. (2002) In-situ reflectance spectroscopy – analysing techniques for high-resolution pigment logging in sediment cores. International Journal of Earth Sciences 91: 950-954.

16. Data structure and data format

This entry contains the following data folders and subfolders (in alphabetical order):

Chronology
      L15_C14_data.csv – radiocarbon age data for Lake L15
      L15_Pb210_S3.csv – Pb-210 age data for Lake L15
      CRS is constant rate of supply model; DMAR is dry mass accumulation rate

Geochemistry & sedimentology

GEOTEK data folder containing:
L15_GEOTEK_MSCL.csv – GEOTEK MSCL data for cores from Lake L15 (GPS Lake)

ITRAX data folder containing:
L15_H2 folder containing:
document_XRF.txt – run and set up data for the core section XRF scan
document_XRAD.txt – run and set up data for the core section radiography scan
optical.tif – raw optical image of the core section scan
optical1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed optical image of the core section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
optical2.tif – vertically rotated version of optical1.tif
radiograph.tif – raw X ray image of the core section scan
radiograph1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed X ray image of the core section scan section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
result.txt – summary set up and cps datafile for the core section
sumspectra.txt – average spectra output datafile the core section
XRF-spectra.zip folder – individual run data and spectra channel energy data for the core section in sequence from the top of the section, e.g., L000001.txt, L00001.txt etc. 
L15_H2_Cr_2mm_cps.csv – filtered cps X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data 
L15_H2_Cr_2mm__%TSN.csv - %TSN (percentage of the total scatter normalised sum) X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data
L15_H2_MS.csv – X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) MS data
L15_H16 folder containing:
document_XRF.txt – run and set up data for the core section XRF scan
document_XRAD.txt – run and set up data for the core section radiography scan
optical.tif – raw optical image of the core section scan
optical1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed optical image of the core section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
optical2.tif – vertically rotated version of optical1.tif
radiograph.tif – raw X ray image of the core section scan
radiograph1.tif – autotune/autocontrast/autocolour processed X ray image of the core section scan section scan in Photoshop v23.2.0
result.txt – summary set up and cps datafile for the core section
sumspectra.txt – average spectra output datafile the core section
XRF-spectra.zip folder – individual run data and spectra channel energy data for the core section in sequence from the top of the section, e.g., L000001.txt, L00001.txt etc. 
L15_H16_Cr_2mm_cps.csv – filtered cps X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data 
L15_H16_Cr_2mm__%TSN.csv - %TSN (percentage of the total scatter normalised sum) X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) data
L15_H16_MS.csv – X ray fluorescence (XRF) core scanning (XRF-CS) MS data

SPECIM data folder containing:
L15_H2_SPECIM.csv – summary output of Specim data used
L15_H16_SPECIM.csv – summary of Specim data used
L15_H2_SPECIM_archive.zip – archive of Specim imagery and data 
L15_H16_SPECIM_archive.zip – archive of Specim imagery and data

Lake chemistry data folder containing:
L15_Water_chemistry.csv 

Notes: DO%: Run for 10-15 minutes to stabilise inside sealed beaker with damp sponge; Calibrated using atmospheric pressure of 1012.0 mbar (from Garmin barGPS); Air temp = -1oC; stable temp/press
Photos Folder containing:

L15_site_photos

17. Access constraints
None after publication but a log in for reviewers to access an embargoed dataset is needed.

18. Use constraints
NERC-funded data, so the Open Government Licence applies.




